Edna Hatfield Edmondson correspondence, 1922 C705
Indiana University Archives
Edna Hatfield Edmondson correspondence
1922
Indiana University Archives
Edmondson, Edna Hatfield, 1886-1973
C705
0.2 cubic feet 1 box
Edna Hatfield Edmondson was a faculty member in the Indiana University Extension Division from 1919 through 1942. This collection consists of letters that Edmondson wrote to Frank R. Elliott, Director of Publicity at IU, while she was on a trip to Japan with the Indiana University baseball team in April-May 1922.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Edna Hatfield Edmondson was a faculty member in the Indiana University Extension Division from 1919 through 1942. She was born Edna Elder Hatfield in Magnet, Perry County, Indiana on January 5, 1886. In 1907, she enrolled at Indiana University, where she earned a bachelor's degree in economics (1911), followed by a master's degree (1914) and PhD (1917) in sociology. On July 31, 1913, she married Clarence Edmund Edmondson (1883-1944), who taught human physiology and social hygiene at Indiana University from 1913-1944 and was Dean of Men from 1925-1944.
Edmondson began her work in the Extension Division in 1919 as an instructor with a focus on child welfare work in Indiana. She became an assistant professor in Sociology in June 1921, at which rank she retired in July 1942. Both Edna and Clarence Edmondson accompanied the Indiana University baseball team on its April-May 1922 trip to Tokyo, Japan.
Edmondson passed away in Los Angeles, California, on December 7, 1973.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of several letters and postcards that Edna Hatfield Edmondson wrote to Frank R. Elliott, Director of Publicity at Indiana University, while she was on a trip to Japan with the Indiana University baseball team in April-May 1922. The majority of Edmondson's letters are descriptions of the games that IU played against the Waseda University team. She typically provided a brief overview of the game, a list of plays for each inning, and clippings from the English-language Japan Advertiser.
Other letters describe the team's arrival in Japan, including going through customs and attending a banquet at Waseda University; the IU team members' reactions to an earthquake that occurred on April 29 or 30, 1922; and meeting with Japanese IU alumni in Tokyo. Edmondson's April 22 letter includes photo postcards of the Waseda, Keio, and IU baseball teams.
Related Material
The Leonard C. Ruckelhaus papers, Collection C519, includes a diary, scrapbook, photographs, and correspondence kept by Ruckelshaus, a member of the IU baseball team, during the 1922 trip to Japan.
Related photographs may be available in the Archives Photographs Collection.
Acquisition Information
Accession: 2014/006
Provenance
Transferred to the University Archives at an unknown date.
- Edna Hatfield Edmondson correspondence, 1922
  - April 15, 1922 (Box 1)
  - April 17, 1922 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Letter includes description of dinner given by Japanese IU alumni.
  - April 19, 1922 (Box 1)
    Letter about a banquet held by Waseda University, including quotes from speeches by representatives of both universities.
  - April 22, 1922 (Box 1)
  - April 23, 1922 (Box 1)
  - April 26, 1922 (Box 1)
  - April 27, 1922 (Box 1)
    Includes postcards bearing photographs of the Indiana, Waseda, and Keio teams.
  - April 30, 1922 (Box 1)
    Includes account of Indiana team members' reactions to an earthquake
  - May 2, 1922 (Box 1)
  - May 4, 1922 (Box 1)
  - May 6, 1922 (Box 1)
  - May 8, 1922 (Box 1)
  - May 9, 1922 (Box 1)